Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter collection, Inclusive:1927-2004, undated, Bulk: 1927-1955, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter collection
Inclusive:1927-2004, undated, Bulk: 1927-1955, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3838
Rueter, Christian H.W., 1909 - 1977
3 document boxes and 1 oversized box.
The Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter collection consists of correspondence, certificates, postcards, artworks, photographs, and biographical information collected by Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter and his family.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Christian Henry William Rueter was born 1909 October 22. He was the son of German-American parents Herman and Elise Rueter, who lived in a farmhouse located in Robinson, Texas. Christian was the youngest of nine children. In his youth, Rueter attended Robinson Academy.
Rueter's desire to be an aviator was a life long passion. In order to join the Army Air Corps, it was a requirement to have a minimum of two years of college. As a result, he enrolled at Baylor University in Waco, Texas, from 1928 September 14 to 1930 June 6. While at Baylor, Rueter played the clarinet in the Baylor Cadet Band. After completing two years of schoolwork, he applied for aviation training at Randolph Field in San Antonio, Texas.
In 1934, Rueter was accepted to aviation school and joined the 143rd Infantry of the Texas National Guard band section. He eventually transferred to the Air Corps training center in Randolph Field and in 1935 February was transferred to the Army Air Force. Rueter completed his Air Corps training school in San Antonio, Texas, in 1935. In 1936 February, he acquired his wings and graduated from the Air Corps Advanced Flying School at Kelly Field, becoming a flying cadet for a year. Rueter was eventually stationed at Langley Field, Virginia. He was promoted to Second Lieutenant on 1938 October 1.
Amid Rueter's busy career, in 1939 June, he married Alexine Turner of Mt. Sterling, Kentucky.
In 1940, Rueter was once again promoted and transferred to Tampa Army Base in Florida serving as a pilot and operations officer in the 43rd Bombing Squadron. Later on 1940 September 9, he was appointed First Lieutenant in the Army and late in 1941 October 1 was promoted to First Lieutenant in the Air Corps in the Regular Army.
During World War II, Rueter's career continued to prosper. In 1942 April, he served as a Squadron Commander of B-24s for the North African campaign. He was awarded the Distinguished Flying Cross for leading an American bomber raid on Italy, and he also served with the Ninth Bomber Command in the Middle East and as a commander of the 97th Combat WIng in Europe. Rueter also served in the Balkans, the Mediterranean, and was later transferred to England.
Throughout his military career, Rueter served in multiple notable missions. One of his most notable achievements as a bomber pilot was his role as the leader of the first United States raid on Italy. Rueter led successful raids on Tripoli and was the Deputy Commander of the raid on Naples Harbor and the port facilities. During World War II, he also piloted a plane that carried the Archbishop Francis Spellman to Cairo.
After the completion of his service during World War II, Rueter in 1946 became a member of the Regular Army Examining Board in Selfridge Field Michigan. On 1948 July 1, he was appointed Lieutenant Colonel in the United States AIr Force. Rueter eventually served as the air force chief of staff at National Headquarters, Civil Air Patrol, Ellington Air Force Base. In 1949, he was assigned to the Military Air Transport Service (MATS) in Washington D.C. and was assigned to the strategy and mobilization branch at the headquarters. Late in 1949 August 4, Rueter completed training a group in the New York Air National Guard. On 1950 January 25, Rueter completed the Armed Forces Staff College in Norfolk Virginia. In 1954 July 29 he was awarded the Legion of Merit, Far East Command for his outstanding performance from 1952 November 24 to 1963 May 20. He was also awarded the Air Force Commendation medal for his service from 1959 October 5 to 1963 May 13.
After serving in the Air Force for more than 29 years, Rueter retired 1963 May 29 in the Houston Texas area. In his retirement, he enjoyed a variety of recreational activities such as golfing and boating. Rueter and his wife lived in Seabrook, Texas until his death on 1977 January 1. He is buried in Robinson Cemetery.
Scope and Content
The Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter collection consists of documents, photographs, a book of National Geographic Society maps, certificates, and a large portrait painting.
The chronology of this collection begins in 1927 and ends in 2004. The Photographic Materials series is the largest in the collection. These photographs cover the span of Rueter's military career and a portion of his personal life. There is also a small collection of photographs of Clark Gable flying military planes and in uniform during World War II.
Arrangement
The Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter collection was not organized prior to this finding aid. There was no previous inventory. The photographic materials and manuscripts were grouped together respectively.
Currently, the Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter collection is arranged in five series. I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, III. Photographic Materials, IV. Maps and V. Artifacts.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3838. Acquired 2013-03-06
Related Resources
Related references
Army Air Corps Library. "97th Bombardment Wing." Army Air Corps Library and Museum. Accessed 2013 March 20.
"Distinguished Service." The Baylor Lariat. Baylor University, Waco TX 1944 July 21. Accessed 2013 March 20.
Maurer, Maurer, editor. Air Force Combat Units of World War II. Washington D.C.: Department of the Air Force Government Print Officer, 1961.
"Regular Air Force Retired List". Air Force Register, 1996, Vol. 2. Accessed 2013 March 20.
Wall, Richard, editor. "The 1930 Round-Up". Baylor University, Waco, TX, 1930. Accessed 2013 March 2013.
Wood, Margaret-Jean, editor. "The 1944 Round-Up of Service." Baylor University, Waco, TX, 1944. Accessed 2013 March 20.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University -- History, Military.
Subjects
Air warfare -- History -- 20th century.; Postcards.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genres
Certificates.; Correspondence.; Maps.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1938-1943; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Correspondence series includes letters detailing Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter's military service, letters concerning specific awards he received, a telegram to his wife, and a letter from Pat M. Neff requesting Rueter's participation in updating his records at Baylor University.
  - Correspondence, 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Literary Productions, 1927-2004, undated; 2
  The Literary Productions series consists of documents which include a biographical history of Christian Henry William Rueter written by his wife Alexine Rueter, a history of the Rueter family's church, Rueter's collected certificates from his military service, a portait painting, clippings detailing Rueter's career and a collection of postcards.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Postcards
  - Biographical Materials: Christian Henry William Rueter, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin: "History of St. John United Church of Christ", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificates, 1927-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Portrait Painting of Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings (1 of 2), 1940-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings (2 of 2), 1940-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Postcards, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certificates: General, 1939-1963 (Box [1059] OVZ, Folder 6)
  - Certificate: New York Air National Guard, 1949 (Box [1059] OVZ, Folder 7)
- Photographic Materials, 1928-1965, undated; 3
  The Photographic Materials series includes a collection of photographs dated throughout Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter's life. The materials have been organized according to their subject matter.
  Photogravure print; Tintypes
  - Airplanes (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Airplanes (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Buildings, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clark Gable, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter, 1936-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter and family, 1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General (1 of 2), 1928-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General (2 of 2), 1928-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Men in Uniform, 1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Portraits of Colonel Chris H.W. Rueter, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Tintypes, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Copies of Photographs, 1935-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rueters, undated (Box [1059] OVZ, Folder 14)
- Maps, 1943-1952; 4
  The Maps series consists of National Geographic maps collected from throughout the world and a National Geographic Society Maps book in which the maps were originally stored. This map book was compiled by Chris Rueter for his father, so that he would be able to follow him during his travels.
  - The National Geographic Magazine Maps Book, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Africa, 1950 March (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Asia and Adjacent Areas, 1951 March (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Bible Lands and the Cradle of Western Civilization, 1946 December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Canada, Alaska and Greenland, 1947 June (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Central Europe, 1951 September (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Countries of the Caribbean, 1947 October (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Eastern South America, 1955 March (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Europe and the Near East, 1949 June (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Japan and Korea, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Northern Africa, 1954 December (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Pacific Ocean, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Geographic Magazine: South America, 1950 October (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Southeast Asia, 1955 September (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National Geographic Magazine: The Top of the World, 1949 October (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - National Geographic Magazine: Western Europe, 1950 December (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Artifacts, undated; 5
  The Artifacts series includes an unidentified flight squadron patch and a painting of Colonel Chris H.W. Reuter.
  Electronic Resources
  Collection Files
  - Squadron Patch, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Painting, Colonel Chris H.W. Reuter, undated (Folder 2)